Finding Aid for Adelaide J. Hart papers, 1948-1980, 1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Adelaide J. Hart papers
1948-1980
1995
1948-1970
Hart, Adelaide J., 1900-1995
851450 Aa 2
Vice chairman of the Democratic Party State Central Committee, primarily during the gubernatorial administration of G. Mennen Williams. Office files concerning party conventions, election issues, and the work of the state central committee, particularly the role of women in the party and the Women for Humphrey organization during the election of 1968; and scrapbooks and photographs.
11.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Adelaide Hart (donor no. 5150 ), October 1970.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Adelaide Hart was a devoted and tireless worker for the Michigan Democratic party throughout the Williams's era and into the 1960s. Along with Democratic state chairman Neil Staebler, Hart, as vice chairman, was a talented and meticulous organizer of party affairs. Given responsibility for the details of fund raising, party meetings, and women's activities, Hart deserves much credit for the revitalization of the party in the 1950s, especially for the increased participation of women in party activities.
Born April 24, 1900 in Saginaw, Michigan, Hart was educated and employed as a music teacher in the Detroit school system. Politics, however, was her first love. She began her active, political involvement on the local level in 1948 when she was elected precinct delegate and member of the executive board of the 17th congressional district in Wayne County. In 1951, the party in convention selected her as vice chairman. She served here from 1951 to 1961 and then again from 1963 to 1967. Within the party, Hart was chairman of the Michigan Federation of Democratic Women, where she helped to develop the annual Democratic Women's Day.
Beyond Democratic party affairs, Hart also served as a delegate and Democratic caucus chairman at the Michigan constitutional convention of 1961-1962, and as a member of the Michigan Mental Health Commission, 1960-1963. She was also vice president and executive secretary of the Detroit Federation of Teachers.
Adelaide J. Hart died July 22, 1995.
The Hart papers consist almost entirely of files created in her capacity as Democratic vice chairman and as member of the Democratic party 17th congressional district. The files have been maintained in their original order by topic. National Democratic Conventions; State Democratic Conventions; Election Campaigns; State Central Committee General; State Central Committee Women's Activities; Jefferson-Jackson Day Dinner; Topical Files; Conferences; Program Service; Correspondence; Memoranda; and Scrapbooks and Photographs.
Subjects:
Democratic Party (Mich.); Democratic Party (Mich.). State Central Committee.; Hart, Adelaide, 1900-; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Presidents--United States--Election--1968.; United States--Politics and government--1963-1969.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Women for Humphrey.; Women in politics--Michigan.; Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Barkley, Alben William, 1877-1956.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Hart, Adelaide, 1900-; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Political elections.; Staebler, Neil, 1905-2000; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Women.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical/personal
  - Clippings and miscellaneous (Box 1)
    (includes 1995 obituary from the Detroit News)
- Democratic National Conventions
  - 1952 (Box 1)
  - 1956, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1960, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - 1964, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1968, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Democratic State Conventions
  - 1952-1954 (Box 1)
  - 1955 (Box 1)
  - 1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957 (Box 1)
  - 1958, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - 1959, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1960, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1961, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963 (Box 1)
  - 1966 (Box 1)
  - 1967, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1968 (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
- Election Campaigns
  - 1948 (Box 2)
  - (Detroit mayoralty), 1949 (Box 2)
  - 1950, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1952, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1953 (Box 2)
  - 1954, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - 1955, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - 1956, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - 1957 (Box 2)
  - 1958, 15 folders (Box 2)
  - 1959, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - 1960, 16 folders (Box 3)
  - 1961 (Box 3)
  - 1962, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1963 (Box 3)
  - 1964 (Box 3)
  - 1966, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1967 (Box 3)
  - 1968, 9 folders (Box 3)
  - (Detroit mayoralty), 1969 (Box 3)
  - 1970 (Box 3)
- State Central Committee
  - General, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - 1953 (Box 3)
  - 1954, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - 1955 (Box 3)
  - 1956, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 1957 (Box 4)
  - 1958, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 1959 (Box 4)
  - 1960, 16 folders (Box 4)
  - 1961, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - 1962 (Box 4)
  - 1963 (Box 4)
  - 1964 (Box 4)
  - 1965 (Box 4)
  - 1966 (Box 4)
  - 1966 (Box 4)
  - 1967 (Box 4)
  - 1968 (Box 4)
- State Central Committee-Women's Activities
  - 1951, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 1952, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 1953, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - 1954 (Box 4)
  - 1955, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 1956, 10 folders (Box 5)
  - 1957, 8 folders (Box 5)
  - 1958, 8 folders (Box 5)
  - 1959, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - 1960, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - 1962 (Box 5)
  - 1963 (Box 5)
  - 1965 (Box 5)
  - 1967, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - 1968, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Jefferson-Jackson Day Dinner
  - 1951-1963, 12 folders (Box 5)
- Topical Files
  - Civil rights, 1957 (Box 6)
  - Democratic Forum (Paul Douglas), 1967 (Box 6)
  - Education, 1957 (Box 6)
  - Hoffa, James, 1953-1958 (Box 6)
  - Michigan Committee for Civil Rights, 1948-1950 (Box 6)
  - National Committee
    - 1954 (Box 6)
    - 1956 (Box 6)
    - 1958 (Box 6)
  - State Finances, 1959 (Box 6)
  - Williams Day, 1950 (Box 6)
- Conferences
  - 1953 (Box 6)
  - 1955, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - National Conference of the State Chairmen and the Vice Chairmen, 1959 (Box 6)
  - 1960, 6 folders (Box 6)
- Program Services
  - 1950-1953 (Box 6)
  - 1955 (Box 6)
  - 1956 (Box 6)
  - 1957 (Box 6)
  - 1958 (Box 6)
  - 1959 (Box 6)
  - 1960 (Box 6)
  - 1961-1963 (Box 6)
  - 1965 (Box 6)
  - 1968 (Box 6)
- Correspondence
  - With G. Mennen Williams
    - Undated, 1949-1955 (Box 6)
    - 1956-1960 (Box 6)
    - 1961-1971 (Box 6)
  - With Nancy Williams (Box 6)
  - With others (mainly political figures)
    - 1949-1959 (Box 6)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 6)
    - 1962-1965 (Box 6)
    - 1966-1971 (Box 6)
- Memoranda
  - G. Mennen Williams, 1959; 1960-1965 (Box 6)
  - Diary of out-of-state political trips, 1959 (Box 6)
  - From Jim Vinall re higher education and the constitutional convention, 1961 (Box 6)
  - Patrick McNamara and Jimmy Hoffa, late, 1950s (Box 6)
  - Re support of Neil Staebler as chairman of the Democratic State Central Committee, 1964 (Box 6)
- Scrapbooks and Photographs
  - 1951 (Box 9)
    (includes photos of Harry Truman, Alben Barkley, Neil Staebler, and G. Mennen Williams)
  - 1952-1956, 4 volumes (Box 7)
    (includes photos of the 1952 Democratic national convention)
  - 1957-1960, 4 volumes (Box 8)
  - 1961 (Box 9)
    (includes photos of constitutional convention delegates and committee meetings)
  - 1961-1964, 3 volumes (Box 10)
  - 1965-1967, 3 volumes (Box 11)
  - 1968-1970, 3 volumes (Box 12)
  - Photograph album, circa 1970-1980 (Box 12)
    (containing portraits and informal photos of G. Mennen Williams; also earlier photos of Williams, Philip A. Hart, Margaret Price, and others)
  - Photograph album:, 1963-circa 1975 (Box 12)
    include photos from the state constitutional convention, 1963 (and reunion, 1975); also autographed photos of Michigan public figures, ca. 1963-ca. 1975
  - Photographs (Box 12)
    (includes portrait and photos of John Kennedy campaigning in Detroit; also photos from the 1960 Democratic National Convention with informal portraits of G. Mennen Williams)
    (see also oversize box 9)
Related Material
The Hart collection should be used to supplement other collections held by the Michigan Historical Collections of the Bentley Historical Library. These collection include the records of the Democratic Party State Central Committee and the personal papers of Governor G. Mennen Williams and party chairman Neil Staebler.
Adelaide Hart donated her files relating to her activities as a delegate to the state constitutional convention to the Michigan State University Archives and Historical Collections, East Lansing, Michigan.